that it's not so difficult to win someone in order to betray others. Even some of the top dissidents in East Germany collaborated with the Stasi, as for instance Ibrahim Böhme. In 1989, he was the leader of the peaceful revolution and he nearly became the first freely elected Prime Minister of the GDR until it came out that he was an informant. The net of spies was really broad. In nearly every institution, even in the churches or in West Germany, there were many of them. I remember telling a leading Stasi officer, "If you had sent an informant to me, I would surely have recognized him." His answer was, "We didn't send anyone. We took those who were around you." And in fact, two of my best friends reported about me to the Stasi. Not only in my case, informers were very close. For example, Vera Lengsfeld, another leading dissident, in her case it was her husband who spied on her. A famous writer was betrayed by his brother. This reminds me of the novel "1984" by George Orwell, where the only apparently trustable person was an informer. But why did the Stasi collect all this information in its archives? The main purpose was to control the society. In nearly every speech, the Stasi minister gave the order to find out who is who, which meant who thinks what. He didn't want to wait until somebody tried to act against the regime. He wanted to know in advance what people were thinking and planning. The East Germans knew, of course, that they were surrounded by informers, in a totalitarian regime that created mistrust and a state of widespread fear, the most important tools to oppress people in any dictatorship. That's why not many East Germans tried to fight against the Communist regime. If yes, the Stasi often used a method which was really diabolic. It was called Zersetzung, and it's described in another guideline. The word is difficult to translate because it means originally "biodegradation." But actually, it's a quite accurate description. The goal was to destroy secretly the self-confidence of people, for example by damaging their reputation, by organizing failures in their work, and by destroying their personal relationships. Considering this, East Germany was a very modern dictatorship. The Stasi didn't try to arrest every dissident. It preferred to paralyze them, and it could do so because it had access to so much personal information and to so many institutions. Detaining someone was used only as a last resort. For this, the Stasi owned 17 remand prisons, one in every district. Here, the Stasi also developed quite modern methods of detention. Normally, the interrogation officer didn't torture the prisoner. Instead, he used a sophisticated system of psychological pressure in which strict isolation was central. Nearly no prisoner resisted without giving a testimony. If you have the occasion, do visit the former Stasi prison in Berlin and attend a guided tour with a former political prisoner who will explain to you how this worked. One more question needs to be answered: If the Stasi were so well organized, why did the Communist regime collapse? First, in 1989, the leadership in East Germany was uncertain what to do against the growing protest of people. It was especially confused because in the mother country of socialism, the Soviet Union, a more liberal policy took place. In addition, the regime was dependent on the loans from the West. Therefore, no order to crash down the uprising was given to the Stasi. Secondly, in the Communist ideology, there's no place for criticism. Instead, the leadership stuck to the belief that socialism is a perfect system, and the Stasi had to confirm that, of course. The consequence was that despite all the information, the regime couldn't analyze its real problems, and therefore it couldn't solve them. In the end, the Stasi died because of the structures that it was charged with protecting. The ending of the Stasi was something tragic, because these officers were kept busy during the peaceful revolution with only one thing: to destroy the documents they had produced during decades. Fortunately, they had been stopped by human rights activists. That's why today we can use the files to get a better understanding of how a surveillance state functions. Thank you. (Applause) Bruno Giussani: Thank you. Thank you very much. So Hubertus, I want to ask you a couple of questions because I have here Der Spiegel from last week. "Mein Nachbar NSA." My neighbor, the NSA. And you just told us about my neighbor, the spies and the informant from East Germany. So there is a direct link between these two stories or there isn't? What's your reaction as a historian when you see this? Hubertus Knabe: I think there are several aspects to mention. At first, I think there's a difference of why you are collecting this data. Are you doing that for protecting your people against terrorist attacks, or are you doing that for oppressing your people? So that makes a fundamental difference. But on the other hand, also in a democracy, these instruments can be abused, and that is something where we really have to be aware to stop that, and that also the intelligence services are respecting the rules we have. The third point, probably, we really can be happy that we live in a democracy, because you can be sure that Russia and China are doing the same, but nobody speaks about that because nobody could do that. (Applause) BG: When the story came out first, last July, last year, you filed a criminal complaint with a German tribunal. Why? HK: Yeah, I did so because of the second point I mentioned, that I think especially in a democracy, the rules are for everybody. They are made for everybody, so it's not allowed that any institution doesn't respect the rules. In the criminal code of Germany, it's written that it's not allowed to tap somebody without the permission of the judge. Fortunately, it's written in the criminal code of Germany, so if it's not respected, then I think an investigation is necessary, and it took a very long time that the public prosecutor of Germany started this, and he started it only in the case of Angela Merkel, and not in the case of all the other people living in Germany. BG: That doesn't surprise me because — (Applause) — because of the story you told. Seen from the outside, I live outside of Germany, and I expected the Germans to react much more strongly, immediately. And instead, the reaction really came only when Chancellor Merkel was revealed as being wiretapped. Why so? HK: I take it as a good sign, because people feel secure in this democracy. They aren't afraid that they will be arrested, and if you leave this hall after the conference, nobody has to be afraid that the secret police is standing out and is arresting you. So that's a good sign, I think. People are not really scared, as they could be. But of course, I think, the institutions are responsible to stop illegal actions in Germany or wherever they happen. BG: A personal question, and this is the last one. There has been a debate in Germany about granting asylum to Edward Snowden. Would you be in favor or against? HK: Oh, that's a difficult question, but if you ask me, and if I answer honestly, I would give him the asylum, because I think it was really brave what he did, and he destroyed his whole life and his family and everything. So I think, for these people, we should do something, and especially if you see the German history, where so many people had to escape and they asked for asylum in other countries and they didn't get it, so it would be a good sign to give him asylum. (Applause) BG: Hubertus, thank you very much.
que no es tan difícil de convencer a alguien para que traicione a otros. Incluso algunos de los disidentes más famosos de la Alemania Oriental colaboraron con la Stasi, por ejemplo Ibrahim Böhme. En 1989 era el líder de la revolución pacífica y casi es el primer Primer Ministro elegido democráticamente de la RDA sino es porque se descubre que había sido un informante. La red de espías era muy vasta. En casi todas las instituciones, hasta en las iglesias, o en la Alemania Occidental, había muchos de ellos. Recuerdo que le dije a un importante oficial de la Stasi: "Si me hubiera mandado un informante, de seguro lo habría reconocido". Su respuesta fue: "No le mandamos a nadie. Usamos a los que estaban a su alrededor". De hecho, dos de mis mejores amigos me reportaban a la Stasi. No solo en mi caso los informantes era muy allegados. Por ejemplo, para Vera Lengsfeld, otra disidente famosa, su esposo era el que la espiaba. Un escritor famoso fue traicionado por su hermano. Esto me recuerda la novela "1984" de George Orwell, en la que la única persona aparentemente confiable era un informante. Pero ¿por qué la Stasi recolectaba toda esta información en sus archivos? Su propósito principal era controlar la sociedad. En casi todos sus discursos, el ministro de la Stasi daba órdenes de averiguar quién era quién, o quién pensaba qué. No quería esperar hasta que alguien intentara actuar contra el régimen. Quería saber por adelantado lo que la gente pensaba y planeaba. Los alemanes del este sabían que estaban rodeados de informantes, en un régimen totalitario que creaba desconfianza y en un estado de terror colectivo, la herramienta más importante para oprimir a la gente en cualquier dictadura. Por eso no muchos alemanes del este trataron de luchar contra el régimen comunista. Si así fuera, la Stasi usaba un método que era realmente diabólico. Se llamaba Zersetzung, y está descrito en otro lineamiento. La palabra es difícil de traducir porque originalmente significa "biodegradación". Pero es una descripción muy precisa. La meta era destruir secretamente la autoestima de la gente, al dañar su reputación, crear fallas en su trabajo, y destruir sus relaciones personales. Consideren esto, Alemania Oriental, era una dictadura moderna. La Stasi no trató de arrestar a todos los disidentes. Prefería neutralizarlos, y podía hacerlo porque tenía mucho acceso a información personal y a muchas instituciones. Detener a alguien solo se hacía en última instancia. Para ello, la Stasi tenía 17 prisiones preventivas, una en cada distrito. La Stasi había creado unos métodos de detención muy modernos. Normalmente el oficial que interrogaba no torturaba al prisionero. En su lugar se usaba un sofisticado sistema de presión psicológica, donde lo principal era el aislamiento. Casi ningún prisionero se resistía a no dar testimonio. Si tienen la oportunidad, visiten una prisión de la antigua Stasi en Berlín y tomen un tour guiado por un antiguo prisionero político que les explicará cómo funcionaba eso. Hay que responder a otra pregunta: Si la Stasi estaba tan bien organizada, ¿por qué colapsó el régimen comunista? Primero, en 1989, los líderes de la Alemania Oriental no sabían qué hacer contra las crecientes protestas de la gente. Era especialmente confuso porque en la "patria madre" del socialismo, la Unión Soviética, se habían instaurado políticas más liberales. Además, el régimen dependía de los préstamos del Occidente. Por eso no se le dio ninguna orden a la Stasi para aplacar estos levantamientos. Segundo, en la ideología comunista no hay lugar para la crítica. Más bien los líderes estaban convencidos de que el socialismo era un sistema perfecto y que la Stasi tenía que confirmarlo. La consecuencia fue que a pesar de toda la información, el régimen no podía analizar sus problemas verdaderos y por ende, no podía resolverlos. Al final la Stasi dejó de existir gracias a las estructuras que estaba encargada de proteger. El final de la Stasi fue algo trágico porque los oficiales se mantuvieron ocupados durante la revolución pacífica con una sola tarea: destruir los documentos que habían producido por décadas. Afortunadamente, activistas de derechos humanos los detuvieron. Por eso hoy en día podemos usar esos archivos para lograr un mejor entendimiento de cómo funciona el estado de vigilancia. Gracias. (Aplausos) Bruno Giussani: Gracias. Muchas gracias. Hubertus, quiero hacerte un par de preguntas porque aquí tengo el Der Spiegel de la semana pasada. "Mein Nachbar NSA". Mi vecino, la NSA (Agencia de Supervisión Nacional) Y tú nos acabas de hablar acerca de mi vecino, los espías e informantes de la Alemania Oriental. ¿Hay alguna relación directa entre estas dos historias o no? ¿Cuál fue tu reacción como historiador al ver esto? HK: Creo que hay que mencionar varios aspectos. Primero, creo que hay una diferencia en la razón por la que Uds. recogen estos datos. ¿Lo hacen para proteger a su gente contra los ataques terroristas, o lo hacen para oprimir a su gente? Allí está la diferencia fundamental. Pero por otra parte, incluso en una democracia se puede abusar de estas herramientas, y esto es algo por lo que tenemos que estar alerta para pararlo, y para que los servicios de inteligencia respeten las reglas que existen. El tercer punto, probablemente, es que realmente tenemos que apreciar que vivimos en democracia porque puedes estar seguro de que en Rusia y en China se está haciendo lo mismo, pero nadie habla de eso porque nadie puede. (Aplausos) BG: Cuando la historia apareció por primera vez en julio del año pasado, presentaste una demanda criminal ante un tribunal alemán. ¿Por qué? HK: Sí, lo hice por el segundo punto que mencioné, que creo que, especialmente en una democracia, las reglas son para todos. Están creadas para todos, así que no está permitido que ninguna institución no respecte las reglas. En el código criminal alemán está establecido que no se puede espiar a nadie sin el permiso de un juez. Afortunadamente, está establecido en el código criminal alemán así que si no se respecta, creo que es necesaria una investigación. Y tomó mucho tiempo antes de que un fiscal público alemán lo hiciera, y comenzó solo en el caso de Angela Merkel, y no en el caso de todos los habitantes en Alemania. BG: Eso no me sorprende porque —(Aplausos) — por la historia que contaste. Visto desde afuera, vivo fuera de Alemania, esperaba que Alemania reaccionara más fuertemente, inmediatamente. Sin embargo, la reacción vino solo cuando la Canciller Merkel reveló que la estaban espiando. ¿Por qué? HK: Lo tomo como una buena señal porque la gente se siente segura en esta democracia. No temen ser arrestados, y si sales de este auditorio luego de la conferencia, nadie teme que la policía secreta esté afuera y que te vaya a arrestar. Creo que esa es una buena señal. La gente no está realmente atemorizada como pudieran estarlo. Pero por supuesto que creo que las instituciones son responsable de detener las acciones ilegales en Alemania o donde sea que ocurran. BG: Una pregunta personal, y esta es la última. Ha habido un debate en Alemania acerca de darle asilo a Edward Snowden. ¿Estás a favor o en contra? HK: Oh, esa es una pregunta difícil, pero si me preguntas y te respondo honestamente, le daría asilo porque creo que lo que hizo fue muy valiente, y que destruyó toda su vida, su familia, todo. Creo que debemos hacer algo por estos individuos. Especialmente si ves la historia alemana, donde tanta gente tuvo que escapar, y pidió asilo en otros países y no lo obtuvieron, creo que sería una buena señal darle asilo. (Aplausos) BG: Hubertus, muchas gracias.